dr. ir. Rein Houthooft

Happy Elements, Inc. 2 Embarcadero Center San Francisco, CA 94111 USA

Phone: +1 (415) 254 5315

Nationality: Belgium (USA research/STEM O1 visa)

email: rein.houthooft@gmail.com URL: reinhouthooft.github.io

be.linkedin.com/in/reinhouthooft

Summary

Expertise in fundamental AI/ML research, specifically focusing on deep learning, with a strong publication track record. ML engineering and applied research management experience in building high-throughput online recommendation/personalization systems. See reinhouthooft.github.io for a more complete description.

Current position

Head of AI, Happy Elements, Inc. en.happyelements.com/ai

With over 100 million unique monthly active users, Happy Elements is the producer of one of the largest active mobile games worldwide. In 2018 I joined the company to co-found and co-lead its AI lab with the goal of optimizing mobile gaming experience through machine learning. Since its inception, the team grew to over 20 members, with presence both in Beijing and San Francisco. Through the development of algorithms, systems, and models as well as the supporting production infrastructure, the AI lab is able to significantly impact company revenue by increasing the overall player life-time value and retention.

Areas of specialization

Artificial Intelligence • Machine Learning • Software Engineering

Experience

2017-2018	Research Scientist, OpenAI
	search were applied to solve to simulated robotics and game playing problems.
2014-2017	Doctoral Researcher, imec
2016	Machine Learning Research Intern, OpenAI
2012	Software Engineering Intern, Solvace
2011	Combinatorial Optimization Researcher, KU Leuven set.kuleuven.be/codes Collaboration project with ArcelorMittal to optimize supply chain logistics using linear programming and meta-heuristics.
	Education
2014-2017	<i>Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering</i>
2016	Visiting Student Researcher University of California—Berkeley, USA Deep reinforcement learning research with Pieter Abbeel at the Berkeley AI Research Lab (BAIR).
2012-2014 2008-2012	M.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering
	Publications
	Conference articles
2018	Houthooft, R., Chen, R. Y., Isola, P., Stadie, B. C., Wolski, F., Ho, J., Abbeel, P. (2018). Evolved Policy Gradients. In <i>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)</i> , Montreal, Candada
	Stadie, B. C., Yang, G., Houthooft, R., Chen, X., Duan, Y., Yuhuai, W., Abbeel, P., Sutskever, I. (2018). Some Considerations on Learning to Explore via Meta-Reinforcement Learning. In <i>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)</i> , Montreal, Candada
	Plappert, M., Houthooft, R., Dhariwal, P., Sidor, S., Chen, R.Y., Chen, X., Asfour, Y., Abbeel, P., and Andrychowicz, M. (2018). Parameter Space Noise for Exploration. <i>International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)</i> .

- Tang, H., Houthooft, R., Foote, D., Stooke, A., Chen, X., Duan, Y., Schulman, J., De Turck, F., and Abbeel, P. (2017). #Exploration: A study of count-based exploration for deep reinforcement learning. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)*, Long Beach, USA
- Houthooft, R., Chen, X., Duan, Y., Schulman, J., De Turck, F., and Abbeel, P. (2016). VIME: Variational information maximizing exploration. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* (NIPS), pages 1109–1117, Barcelona, Spain.
 - Chen, X., Duan, Y., Houthooft, R., Schulman, J., Sutskever, I., and Abbeel, P. (2016). InfoGAN: Interpretable representation learning by information maximizing generative adversarial nets. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)*, pages 2172–2180, Barcelona, Spain.
 - Duan, Y., Chen, X., Houthooft, R., Schulman, J., and Abbeel, P. (2016). Benchmarking deep reinforcement learning for continuous control. In *Proceedings of the 33rd International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, pages 1329–1338, New York, USA.
 - Houthooft, R., De Boom, C., Verstichel, S., Ongenae, F., and De Turck, F. (2016). Structured output prediction for semantic perception in autonomous vehicles. In *Proceedings of the 30th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence*, Phoenix, Arizona, USA.
- Houthooft, R., Sahhaf, S., Tavernier, W., De Turck, F., Colle, D., and Pickavet, M. (2015). Robust geometric forest routing with tunable load balancing. In *Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM)*, pages 1382–1390, Hong Kong, P.R. China.
- Houthooft, R., Sahhaf, S., Tavernier, W., De Turck, F., Colle, D., and Pickavet, M. (2014). Fault-tolerant greedy forest routing for complex networks. In *Proceedings of the 6th International Workshop on Reliable Networks Design and Modeling (RNDM)*, pages 1–8, Barcelona, Spain.
 - De Backere, F., Hanssens, B., Heynssens, R., Houthooft, R., Zuliani, A., Verstichel, S., Dhoedt, B., and De Turck, F. (2014). Design of a security mechanism for RESTful Web service communication through mobile clients. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS)*, pages 1–6, Krakow, Poland.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Houthooft, R. and De Turck, F. (2016). Integrated inference and learning of neural factors in structural support vector machines. *Pattern Recognition*, 59:292–301.
- Houthooft, R., Ruyssinck, J., van der Herten, J., Stijven, S., Couckuyt, I., Gadeyne, B., Ongenae, F., Colpaert, K., Decruyenaere, J., Dhaene, T., and De Turck, F. (2015). Predictive modelling of survival and length of stay in critically ill patients using sequential organ failure scores. *Artificial Intelligence in Medicine*, 63(3):191 207.
 - Houthooft, R., Sahhaf, S., Tavernier, W., De Turck, F., Colle, D., and Pickavet, M. (2015). Optimizing robustness in geometric routing via embedding redundancy and regeneration. *Networks*, 66(4):320–

PATENT APPLICATIONS

2016

Houthooft, R., Verstichel, S., Debilde, B., and Foster, C. A controller for a working vehicle. E.U. Patent Application No. 16177346.0 - 1905. U.S. Patent Application No. 15/199,090. Filed 30 June 2016.